A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, A-E FA391
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Beard, Mary
  - 1934, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 112 pages (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 102)
    Organized according to interview or view, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Nursing education programs both domestic and international- are discussed and schools of nursing located within the U.S. are visited and surveyed. Main topics in this diary include reorganizing public health nursing programs in Washington County, New York, Vanderbilt University, University of Toronto and New York Hospital. Beard is also involved with the selection process and mentorship of RF fellowship nursing applicants. A copy of "Act of Parliament of the Council of the School of Nursing, University of Toronto" is included as well as an outline review of New York Hospital's budgetary crisis regarding its nursing services and how to build up present nursing organization.
    Diaries; Public health nursing; Nursing care plans; Nursing
  - 1935, Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary; 92 pages (Reel M Bea 2, Frame 244, Box 30A)
    The diary is organized according to interview and visit. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellowsboth American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. Throughout the year, development of public health nursing programs continues at Columbia University, Vanderbilt University and Washington County, New York. Beard opens discussion for development of school of nursing between Russell Sage College in Troy, New York, and Albany Medical School and Albany General Hospital. Brief travels to Europe, specifically England to discuss organizing and supplying grant money to set up Florence Nightingale School of Nursing in England. A copy of "East Harlem Nursing and Health Service" is included.
    Diaries; United States; Public health nursing; Nursing care plans; Nursing; France; England
  - 1936, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 136 pages (Reel M Bea 2, Frame 351, Box 30A)
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. Beard continues to develop, reorganize and establish nursing education programs at various institutions around the country such as Vanderbilt University, Russell Sage, John Hopkins and Skidmore College. Beard also details the limitations and setbacks of developing public health nursing education programs at the advanced level. The diary describes the hardships of rural Southern nurses and how the Tennessee Valley Authority Health Study makes an impact on the region. Beard sets up talks to develop a School of Nursing at University of California at Los Angeles. She travels to Panama to develop nursing education programs in the region. A copy of "Minutes of the Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Nursing, of the Department of Health", a graph of "Various Types of Schools of nursing in the United States (1936)", "Minutes of the Council of Course Directors" and "Visiting Nurse Association" documents, a pamphlet entitled "Baby Record" put out by the Child Welfare Division, Department of Health and Sanitation, Seattle, Washington as well as a pamphlet distributed by the Public Education Association entitled "what It is and What It Does" are included.
    Nursing care plans; Nursing; Canada; Diaries; United States; Public health nursing; Panama
  - Trip Index, 1937; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation (Reel M Bea 2, Frame 502, Box 30A)
    Trip Index to Diary:1937; 19 pages.
  - 1937, Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary; 128 pages (Reel M Bea 2, Frame 521, Box 30A)
    Scope and Content note
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows- both American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. She continues to develop nursing education programs around the country. Beard travels to Scandinavia and discusses public health nursing programs. The entries outline nursing education curriculum and legislation affecting them. She also travels to England where she details the measures that the Florence Nightingale International Foundation have adopted and haven't. Included are "Conference on Public Health Nursing" documents.
    United States; Public health nursing; Diaries; Sweden; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Finland; England; Canada
  - 1938, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 58 pages (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 659)
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both foreign and domestic. She summarizes the interviews with the current fellows. Beard attends numerous conferences and travels to the southern United States to detail public health nursing. Her travels take her to England and there she outlines the Florence Nightingale Foundation's objectives for their public health nursing programs as well as detailing public health nursing teacher qualifications for London University. Included are "conference o Eugenic and Birth Control of the American Eugenics Society" schedule and itinerary "Visits made by Miss Mary Beard in London on Wednesday July 13th and Thursday July 14th."
    Nursing; Nursing care plans; Diaries; Public health nursing; United States
- Beck, Glenn H.
  - 1969 (Box 31)
- Bell, Philip W.
  - 1963-1964 (Box 31)
  - 1965 (Box 31)
  - 1966 (Box 31)
- Bertheau, Rudolf C.
  - 1925-1928 (Box 31)
- Bevier, George
  Bolivia; Colombia
  - 1935 (Box 32)
  - 1936 (Box 32)
  - 1940, 1945-1947 (Box 32)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 32)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 33)
- Black, Joseph E.
  - 1963 (Box 33)
  - 1964 January-June (Box 33)
  - West Africa and Unindexed Diary, CHECK 1964 July-December (Box 34)
  - 1965 January-June (Box 34)
  - 1965 July-December (Box 34)
  - 1966 January-June (Box 35)
  - 1966 July-December (Box 35)
  - 1967 January-June (Box 35)
  - 1967 July-December (Box 36)
  - 1968 January-July (Box 36)
  - 1968 August-December (Box 36)
  - 1969 January-June (Box 37)
  - 1969 July-December (Box 37)
  - 1970 January-June (Box 37)
  - 1970 July-December (Box 38)
  - 1971 January-June (Box 38)
  - 1971 July-December (Box 38)
  - 1972 (Box 39)
  - 1973 (Box 39)
  - 1974 (Box 39)
  - 1975 (Box 40)
  - 1976 (Box 40)
  - 1977 (Box 40)
  - 1978 (Box 41)
- Boyce, Alfred Mullikin
  Latin America
  - 1968 (Box 41)
  - 1969 (Box 41)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 42)
- Brackett, Elizabeth W.
  - 1942-1943 (Box 42)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 42)
  - 1947 (Box 43)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 43)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 43)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 44)
- Bradfield, Richard
  Philippines; Mexico; Asia
  - 1955 (Box 44)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 44)
- Bradley, William Lee
  - 1970 (Box 45)
- Braga, Ernani P.
  - 1957-1961 (Box 45)
- Bronte, D. Lydia
  - 1973-1975 (Box 45)
  - 1976 January-June (Box 46)
  - 1976 July-December (Box 46)
  - 1977 (Box 46)
  - 1978 (Box 47)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 47)
- Brown, Dorothy E.
  - 1964-1966 (Box 47)
    Diary is unaccounted for and is currently unavailable for scholarly access
- Brown, Robert Z.
  - 1968 July 31-September 9 (Box 47)
    Arrangement note
    This volume was disbound and is housed in Folders 1-4 of Box 10.
  - 1968 October 24-December 6 (Box 47)
  - 1969 January 22-December 22 (Box 47)
  - 1970 March 2-July 4 (Box 47)
- Bryant, John H.
  - 1964 December- 1965 April 24 (Box 48)
    This volume was disbound and is housed in Folders 5-10 of Box 10.
  - 1965 April 25-August (Box 48)
  - 1965 August 20-September (Box 48)
  - 1965 October-December (Box 48)
  - 1966 February-August (Box 48)
  - 1966 September- 1967 January (Box 48)
    The spine label on this volume, which reads "1966-", is incorrect.
- Buchanan, Norman S.
  - 1947-1950 (Box 49)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 49)
  - 1957 (Box 50)
  - 1958 (Box 50)
- Buchwalter, Ellen Shapiro (Mrs. Steven Buchwalter)
  - Diary, Notes, Memos, 1981-1982 (Box 50)
  - Diary, Notes, Memos, 1983 (Box 51)
  - Diary, Notes, Memos, 1984 (Box 51)
  - 1989 (Box 52)
  - Grantmakers in the Arts
    - Volume 1, 1984-1985 (Box 52)
    - Volume 2, 1986-1987 (Box 52)
    - Volume 3, 1988-1992 (Box 53)
    - Volume 4, November 1989 (Box 53)
    - Volume 5: Chicago Conference, 1988 (Box 53)
    - Volume 6: Meetings, January-May 1989 (Box 54)
    - Volume 7, Meetings: Boston, September 1989 (Box 54)
    - Volume 8: Reception, Boston, April 1990 (Box 54)
- Bugher, John C.
  John Clifford Bugher was born September 26, 1901 in Upland, Indiana. He attended the Taylor University in Upland and was a mathematics instructor there while a student. He graduated in 1920 with a Bachelor of Science degree. Bugher then attended the University of Michigan, where he received a second undergraduate degree in 1921. He worked at the University of Michigan as an assistant Bacteriology instructor until 1926 when he enrolled in the University of Michigan Medical School. On April 1, 1926, he married Elizabeth Foust. Bugher graduated from the Medical School in 1929 and became a full-time instructor in Bacteriology. From 1933 until 1937, he remained at the University of Michigan as an Assistant Professor in Pathology. In 1938, he joined the Rockefeller Foundation's International Health Division. He assisted in research at the Yellow Fever Laboratory in Bogota, Columbia from 1940 to 1943, when he went to Lagos, Nigeria to start their Yellow Fever Institute. He stayed in Nigeria as the director of the Institute until 1948. For his work on yellow fever, Bugher received the Cruz de Boyaca from the Columbian government, honorary doctorates from Taylor University and the University of Michigan, and honorary appointment as a Commander in the Order of the British Empire.
  During 1951-52, he served as a consultant for nuclear affairs to the Rockefeller Foundation, before leaving to serve as Deputy Director (and later Director) of the Atomic Energy Commission's Division of Biological and Medical Sciences. Until he left the post in 1955, he defended government testing of nuclear testing against critics who suggested that it might have an impact on the health of Americans. From April 1955 through March 1959, Bugher was Director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Division of Medical Education and Public Health. Subsequently, until his retirement in 1966, Bugher was the Director of the Puerto Rico Nuclear Center.
  Bugher was a prolific author who wrote a number of important works about medical science and nuclear issues, including several textbooks of medical science and biology, Epidemiology of Jungle Yellow Fever in Columbia (1944), Progress of Nuclear Energy (1956), and numerous scientific articles. After retirement, he and his wife moved to Delray Beach, Florida, where he worked on a book about the technical uses of radioactive isotopes in biological research. John Bugher died in 1970 in Palm Beach, Florida.
  - 1943-1947 (Box 55)
- Burden, Robert P.
  - 1949-1951 (Box 55)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 55)
  - 1955 (Box 55)
  - 1956 (Box 56)
  - 1957 (Box 56)
  - 1958 (Box 56)
  - 1959 (Box 57)
- Burke, Alexander W.
  - 1928-1929 (Box 57)
  - 1933-1936 (Box 57)
- Cahn, Steven M.
  - 1979-1981 (Box 57)
- Carr, Henry P.
  - 1938-1939 (Box 58)
    Not complete.
  - 1946-1951 (Box 58)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 58)
- Carter, William S.
  India
  - 1924-1928 (Box 59)
  - 1929 (Box 59)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 59)
  - Fellowship, 1930-1931 (Box 60)
  - 1932-1934 (Box 60)
  - Fellowship, 1932-1934 (Box 60)
- Causey, Ottis R.
  Philippines; Nigeria; Brazil
  - 1939-1942, 1945-1947, 1950-1955 (Box 61)
  - 1956-1961 (Box 61)
- Chadwell, Harris Marshall
  - 1946 (Box 62)
  - 1947 (Box 62)
  - 1948 (Box 62)
- Chandler, Robert Flint, Jr.
  Robert F. Chandler, Jr. was an agricultural sciences officer for the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) and Founding Director of the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) and Asian Vegetable Research and Development Center (AVRDC). He was one of a generation of RF agricultural scientists working to eradicate global famine in the decades following World War II.
  Chandler was born in Columbus, Ohio on June 22, 1907. He earned his B.S. degree in horticulture from the University of Maine in 1929, and his Ph.D. in pomology at the University of Maryland in 1934. He spent the first two decades of his career in academia, first as a forest soils professor at Cornell University, and then as Dean of Agriculture and Director of the Agricultural Experiment Station at the University of New Hampshire. Chandler served as President of the University of New Hampshire from 1950 to 1954.
  In 1946, Chandler took a brief leave from Cornell to work as a Soils Scientist in the RF's Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP). He returned to the Foundation in 1954 to become Assistant Director for Agriculture, and was promoted to Associate Director in 1957. In 1959, Chandler established the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in Los Baos, the Philippines, which sought to fight famine in Asia by increasing rice production. Under Chandler's directorship IRRI staff dramatically boosted rice yields through the development of new varieties, including the IR8 "miracle rice." Chandler retired from the IRRI in 1972, and documented the Institute's history in his 1992 book, An Adventure in Applied Science: A History of the International Rice Research Institute.
  From 1972 to 1975, Chandler served as founding director of the Asian Vegetable Research and Development Center, a research institute in Taiwan focused on developing vegetable crops in Asia's tropical regions. The AVRDC successfully developed high-yielding, heat-tolerant tomato plants, as well as other vegetable varieties suited to tropical conditions.
  Chandler continued working to eradicate world hunger long after his retirement in 1975. He served as an advisor and consultant for the Rockefeller Foundation, Ford Foundation, Near East Foundation, and the U.S. Agency for International Development, among others. He received several awards including the International Rice Year Award from the Indian Council of Agricultural Research in 1966, the Star of Distinction from Pakistan in 1968, the Star of Merit from Indonesia in 1972, the Golden Heart Award from the Philippines in 1972, and the Order of the Brilliant Star from China in 1975. In 1988, he was awarded the prestigious World Food Prize.
  Chandler died on March 23, 1999, at the age of 91. In a memorial symposium honoring Chandler, plant pathologist and Nobel laureate Norman E. Borlaug described him as "one of those pioneers whose boundless energy and enthusiasm--and complete dedication to a cause--helped to make rice available for hundreds of millions of people in the developing world."
  Philippines; Mexico; India; Taiwan
  - 1954-1955 (Box 63)
  - 1956 (Box 63)
  - 1957 (Box 63)
  - 1958 (Box 64)
  - 1959 (Box 64)
  - 1960 (Box 64)
  - 1961 (Box 64)
  - 1962-1967 (Box 65)
  - 1968-1971 (Box 65)
  - 1972-1975 (Box 66)
- Christie, John D.
  - 1974-1976 (Box 66)
- Cobb, William C.
  - 1954-1957 (Box 67)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 67)
- Cole, Charles Woolsey
  Chile
  - 1960-1961 (Box 67)
- Cole, Patricia
  - 1973-1974 (Box 68)
- Collins, Ralph Cable
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collins diaries are temporarily unavailable for research.
  Turkey
  - 1925, 1931-1932, 1934-1939 (Box 68)
- Colton, Joel
  Joel Colton was a distinguished historian of modern Europe who specialized in French history and culture. Named the Rockefeller Foundation's (RF) director for humanities in 1974, Colton's appointment marked the Foundation's renewed focus on the humanities, which had not had their own director within the Foundation since 1962. His tenure with the RF was characterized by a commitment to humanities scholarship, public engagement, and a firm belief in the humanities' relevance to public discourse.
  Colton was born on August 23, 1918 in New York City. He earned his B.A. degree at the City College of New York in 1937, and his M.A. in history at Columbia University in 1940. Colton then earned a master's degree in education at City College and worked as a teacher in training at the Bronx High School of Science from 1941 to 1942.
  Colton served in the Army during World War II, including an eighteen month commission as a military intelligence officer in Europe. After the war, Colton returned to Columbia to work toward his doctorate. In 1947, he took a position teaching European history at Duke University, and completed his Ph.D. in 1950. From 1967 to 1974, he served as the chair of the University's history department. In 1974, Colton accepted a position as the Rockefeller Foundation's director for humanities. His leadership reflected his belief that the humanities should play a central role in contemporary life and his commitment to publicly-engaged scholarship. He oversaw the establishment of the Rockefeller Foundation Fellowships in the Humanities to support humanistic scholarship with contemporary relevance. From 1978 to 1980 Colton served as the liaison to the RF-sponsored Commission on the Humanities, which examined the role of the humanities in American education and public life. The Commission's final report, The Humanities in American Life, was published in 1980.
  Colton organized three conferences at the Rockefeller Foundation's Bellagio Center: "Modernization, Economic Development, and Cultural Values" (1978); "Human Rights, Human Needs, and Developing Nations," co-hosted with Malcolm Richardson (1979); and "International Philanthropy and the Humanities," co-hosted with Kathleen McCarthy (1981). Colton took a study leave in 1981, and began working as a consultant to the Foundation. In 1982, he coauthored a history of the RF's humanities work, "The Humanities and 'The Well-Being of Mankind:' The Humanities at The Rockefeller Foundation Since 1928," with Malcolm Richardson. Colton returned to teaching at Duke in 1982, and retired in 1989.
  Colton received fellowships from the Guggenheim Foundation (1957), Rockefeller Foundation (1961-62), and National Endowment for the Humanities (1970-71), and was honored as a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1979. He authored several books, including Compulsory Labor Arbitration in France, 1936-1939 (1951), Leon Blum: Humanist in Politics (1966), and a book for the Time-Life "Great Ages of Man" series, Twentieth Century (1968). He is perhaps best known for coauthoring the classic textbook, A History of the Modern World. First written by Princeton historian R. R. Palmer in 1950, Colton and Palmer (and later a third historian, Lloyd Kramer) collaborated on the subsequent 9 editions. The textbook has been translated into ten languages.
  Joel Colton passed away on April 17, 2011 in Durham, North Carolina.
  - 1974 (Box 69)
  - 1975 (Box 69)
  - 1976 (Box 69)
  - 1977 (Box 70)
  - 1978 (Box 70)
  - 1979 (Box 70)
  - 1980 (Box 71)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 71)
- Compton, Boyd R.
  - 1958 (Box 72)
  - 1959 (Box 72)
  - 1960 (Box 73)
  - 1961 (Box 73)
  - 1962 (Box 74)
  - Trip to Philippines, Thailand, Hawaii, May-June 1962 (Box 74)
  - 1963 January (Box 74)
  - 1963 February (Box 74)
  - 1963 March (Box 74)
  - 1963 April (Box 74)
  - 1963 May (Box 74)
  - 1963 June (Box 74)
  - 1963 July (Box 74)
  - 1963 August (Box 74)
  - Index, 1963 (Box 74)
  - 1963 September-December (Box 75)
  - 1964 (Box 75)
  - Index, 1965
  - 1965 January (Box 75)
  - 1965 February (Box 75)
  - 1965 March (Box 75)
  - 1965 April (Box 75)
  - 1965 May (Box 75)
  - 1965 June (Box 75)
  - 1965 July-December (Box 76)
  - 1966 January-June (Box 76)
  - 1966 July-December (Box 76)
  - 1967 (Box 77)
- Connor, Michael E.
  South America; Central America; Caribbean Area; Mexico
  - 1918, 1924-1925 (Box 77)
- Cook, Joseph A.
  - 1968-1970 (Box 77)
  - 1971-1977 (Box 78)
- Corwin, Janet D.
  - 1944-1948 (Box 78)
- Court, David
  - 1973-1975 (Box 79)
  - Diary, Notes, 1976 (Box 79)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 79)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 79)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 79)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 79)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 80)
- Crawford, Porter J.
  - 1938-1939 (Box 80)
- Crawford, Robert W.
  - 1961 (Box 80)
  - 1962 (Box 81)
  - 1963 (Box 81)
  - 1964 January-June (Box 82)
  - 1964 July-December (Box 82)
  - 1965 January-June (Box 82)
  - 1965 July-December (Box 83)
  - 1966 January-June (Box 83)
  - 1966 July- 1967 May (Box 83)
- Crowell, F. Elisabeth
  Frances Elisabeth Crowell was a staff member of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) and a dedicated nurse and social worker who devoted much of her life to the task of improving nursing education and standards.
  Crowell completed her nursing training in Chicago in 1895. After graduation she moved to Florida, where she served as superintendent and part owner of the Pensacola Infirmary. At the Infirmary, later renamed St. Anthony's Hospital, Crowell opened a school to train nurses.
  Ten years later, Crowell relocated to New York to study social work at the New York School of Philanthropy. In 1906 she began working as a special investigator with the Association of Neighborhood Workers, producing research on the state of midwifery and its role among New York women, especially immigrant populations. She continued to compile research and produce significant studies on this topic while simultaneously serving as Executive Secretary of the Association of Tuberculosis Clinics in New York.
  In 1917 Crowell devoted herself more fully to the eradication of tuberculosis when she joined the International Health Division (IHD) of the RF and began working for its Commission for the Prevention of Tuberculosis in France. As part of the Commission, Crowell trained medical personnel and organized dispensaries in order to help contain the tuberculosis epidemic in post-war France. Crowell remained in France until 1923, when she joined the Division of Studies Program of the RF. The new appointment allowed Crowell to remain in Europe, and it greatly expanded her influence, as she was charged with developing programs in nursing education throughout the continent.
  Crowell left the RF in 1941 and spent her remaining years in Italy. Although retired, she advised the American Red Cross in Italy during World War II. Crowell died in 1950 and was laid to rest in Santa Margherita, Italy, along the Mediterranean coast.
  - 1926, Rockefeller Foundation; Crowell, F. Elizabeth; 19 pages (Reel M Cro 1, Frame 1, Box 84)
    Crowell travels to Italy, Romania, and Yugoslavia and surveys the state of medical facilities, nursing education, and public health teaching in each country. She holds interviews with persons in the nursing and/or medical professions; tours medical and public health facilities; and describes the development of organization of nursing schools. (RF Paris Office)
    Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; Diaries; Nursing
  - 1927, Rockefeller Foundation; Crowell, F. Elizabeth; 168 pages (Box 84, Reel M Cro 1, Frame 20)